Finding Aid for the The Robert Burns Eleazer Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
- Correspondence – Incoming
  - Young, P. B. (Journal and Globe, Norfolk, VA.), 2 (1940, 1942) (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Correspondence Outgoing
  - Correspondence (Outgoing, 1906 – 1929) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence (Outgoing, 1930 – 1939) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence (Outgoing, 1940 – 1942) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence (Outgoing, 1943 – 1948) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence (Outgoing, 1950 – 1959) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence (Outgoing, 1965 – 1971 and undated) (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Biographical Materials
  - Typescript of My First Eighty Years (pages 1 39) (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Typescript of My First Eighty Years (pages 40 – 80) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Typescript of My First Eighty Years (pages 81 – 106) (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - “My First Ninety Years,” printed in The Park Manor Reporter, (October 1967, vol. 1, no. 6) (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - ½” reel-to-reel tape of interview by John Egerton, April 8, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Transcription of interview done by John Egerton, April 8, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Writings Race Relations
  - Typescript of Broadcast to Southern Church Papers (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Typescript of Broadcasting Good Will (3 copies) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Typescript of Candles of Understanding (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Typescript of Church and Race Relations (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Carbon typescript of Christianity and Race Relations (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Carbon typescript of For Such A Time As This (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Typescript of General Lee and Lynch Law (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Typescript of Indicting A Whole People (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Typescript of Indicting A Whole Race (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Typescript of Interracial Cooperation (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Carbon typescript of Interracially Speaking: Current Comments On Matters of Common Concern (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Typescript of Lynching 1946 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Typescript of Lynching for Ten Eventful Years (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Typescript of The Lynching of Allen Green (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Typescript of Lynchings (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Typescript of The Man in Lower Eleven (2 copies) (Box 2)
  - Typescript of New Orleans properly takes pride… (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Typescript of Notes on Talk of R.B. Eleazer before Atlanta Optimist Club (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Typescript of A Plea for Interracial Amity (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Carbon typescript of Post-War Readjustment: Southern Regional Council Recommends Seven-Point Program (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Carbon typescript of Questions That Give Us Pause (2 copies) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Typescript of A Race in Search of Monuments (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Typescript of A Realistic Approach to the Race Problem (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Typescript of Reason, Religion and Race (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Typescript of The Scottsboro Case (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Typescript of The South Shamed and Troubled by Political Demagogues (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Typescript of Southern Leaders Impeach Judge Lynch (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Typescript of Southern Women and the South’s Race Problem (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Typescript of A Southerner Talks To The South (2 copies) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Typescript of Spirituals Based on African Rhythms (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Carbon typescript of Up From The Dust (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Typescript of What The Bible Tells Me About Race Relations (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Carbon typescript of What Do You Know About The Race Problem? (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Writings Race Relations – Education
  - 4 Typescript of Building Better Attitudes: The Educational Work of the Commission on Interracial Cooperation (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Typescript of Educational Program of Interracial Commission (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Typescript of Educational Program: Commission on Interracial Cooperation (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Typescript of Educational Program: Commission on Interracial Commission, Inc. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Typescript of Is This Your Town? (2 copies) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Typescript of Pioneers Plot Race Relations Study (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Typescript of Suggestions for Campus Program on Race Relations (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Typescript of Suggestions for Sunday School and Youth Groups (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Typescript of Southern School Officials Recommend Important Step (2 copies) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Typescript of Southern Schools Foster Racial Understanding (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Typescript of Program Outlines: (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Reason, Religion and Race
    What Say Religion and Reason?
    What Can We Do About It?
  - Typescript of Course Outlines: (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Short Course for Ministers
    The Church in a Changing World
    The Christian and Race
    Basic Principles of Course in Christian Race Relations (2 copies)
    Christian Principles and World Problems
    Discussions on Race Relations
    Human Relations
  - Typescript of Special Course for Adults: Emergent Race Issues 1 page fragment from Lesson 2 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - A Challenge to Southern Schools: Opening Address to Conference On Education for Southern Citizenship, Blue Ridge, NC, August 25-30, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Typescript of Address by Mr. R.B. Eleazer at Teacher’s Conference, Peabody College [Part I] (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Typescript of Address by Mr. R. B. Eleazer at Teacher’s Conference, Peabody College [Part II] (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Transcript of discussion at Peabody College of [Race] Relations Studies in College and Public Schools led by RBE (incomplete mss, pages 2-14) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Carbon typescript of Annual Meeting, Commission on Interracial Cooperation, April 18-19, 1933: Report of Department of Education (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Typescript of Report of Second Interseminary Conference, Atlanta, Georgia, November 19-20, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Typescript of Field Report, (1944, 1947) (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Writings - Methodism
  - Typescript of From General Conference Records…. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Carbon typescript of The Methodist Church: An Overall View (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Carbon typescript of A Report on the Movement for Revision, Methodist Episcopal Church, South 1817-1922 (2 copies) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Carbon typescript of What Some Laymen Think About It (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Holograph copy of Digest of Actions of Methodist General Conferences On Slavery, Drink and Other Social Issues (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Writings Communism
  - Typescript of Cross Currents in Race Relations (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Typescript of Painting The Country Red (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Typescript of Shall Black Go “Red”? (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Typescript of Unraveling “The Red Network” (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Writings Pacifism
  - Typescript of As Eleazer Saw It (clipping attached) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Typescript of The Churches in a World at War (2 copies) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Typescript of I Still Believe (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - ` Typescript of In Lieu of the Atom Bomb (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Typescript of Shall it Be War Again? (2 copies) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Typescript of Suggested Statement on the War in Vietnam, Prepared for the American Friends Service Committee (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Writings Christianity and Social Issues
  - Carbon typescript of Anti Semitism (2 copies) (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Carbon typescript of Biblical Basis for Social Emphasis (4 copies) (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Carbon typescript of Christianity and the World Today (3 copies) (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Carbon typescript of Christianity in an Unchristian World (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Typescript of I’ll Get Even With Him (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Typescript of Religion, as we know, is far older than the Bible… (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Writings Economic Issues
  - Typescript of The Bible and Economic Recovery (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Typescript of Christianity and the Economic Crisis (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Typescript of I believe the question I am to discuss… (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Typescript of Imprisonment for Debt Under Georgia Law (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Typescript of Industry Was Made for Man (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Typescript of In proportion to numbers Negroes are suffering more severely… (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Typescript of The Negro in the Rural South (2 copies) (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Typescript of Prophetic Voices, The Need of the Hour (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Typescript of Save for the personal turn… (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Typescript of What Price Recovery? (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Typescript of Virus in the Blood: An Effort to Diagnose Our Economic Malady (3 copies) (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Writings Press Releases – Clippings
  - Press Releases, Commission on Interracial Cooperation, (1923-1930) (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Press Releases, Commission on Interracial Cooperation, (1931) (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Press Releases, Commission on Interracial Cooperation, (1932-1942) (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Press Releases, Commission on Interracial Cooperation, (no date) [1] (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Press Releases, Commission on Interracial Cooperation, (no date) [2] (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Press Releases, Methodist Board of Education, (1944-1947) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Interracial Trends, Methodist Board of Education, (1944-1945) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Interracial Notes, Methodist Board of Education, (1945-1948) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper and magazine clippings, (1900-1929) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper and magazine clippings, (1932-1949) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper and magazine clippings, (1950-1969) (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper clippings, Letters to the Editor, (1916-1967, undated) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper and magazine clippings, (undated) (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Writings Miscellaneous
  - Notes (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper clippings of obituary for John J. Eagan (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Typescript of Memorial Address for Robert Russa Moton (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Program from Memorial Service for Robert Russa Moton, Dec. 3, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Youth Conference programs and announcements, Christmas poems, Typescript of Gamblers Dominate Midway at Southeastern Fair, (1938) (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Annual Record, Theta Chapter, The Pi Kappa Alpha Fraternity, Southwestern Presbyterian University, June 1924 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Order forms for Commission on Interracial Cooperation educational materials (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Pamphlets Booklets – Brochures
  - “Race issues” in Adult Student, August 1945, p.29-32 (booklet) (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - A Constructive Force in Race Relations, (pamphlet) (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - “The Christian Church and Race,” “The Methodist Social Creed” and “Working for Better Race Relations” in The Church School, February, 1951, pp.4-7, (booklet) (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - A Sane Approach to the Race Problem, “Issued 1930 by The Stabilization Fund of the Commission on Interracial Cooperation,” (oversize booklet) (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Assorted pamphlets, booklets and brochures produced by the Commission on Interracial Cooperation and the Methodist General Board of Education (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Writings By Others
  - Clippings of reviews of Reason, Religion and Race, (1950) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Clippings of reviews of publications by R.B. Eleazer (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Clippings of newspaper and magazine articles (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper clippings and press releases used as background for R.B. Eleazer’s pamphlet Burnt Cork and Crime (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper clippings and press releases used as background for R. B. Eleazer’s writings on “Heroism” (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Manuscripts and fragments (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Course outlines and extracts from Course of Study from Florida, Georgia, Louisiana, Mississippi, Tennessee and Virginia High Schools (2 copies) (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Carbon typescript of Excerpts from Georgia Program for the Improvement of Instruction, (Bulletin No. 2, May 1937) (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Carbon typescript of Race Relations Course and Correlated Work in Arkansas Teacher’s College, Conway, Ark. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - List of Colleges Using Materials of Interracial Commission in Departments and Quantities Indicated, 1936-1942 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Conference programs and findings from Conferences on Education And Race Relations, (1931-1941) (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Comments (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Student Papers (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Reports on high school race relations units of study (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - America’s Tenth Man Student Papers (includes newspaper clippings) (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Pamphlets (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Album
  - Contains 16”x11 ½” scrapbook. Inscribed on first page: (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - This Volume Records (Box 4, Folder 14)
    The Commission of RB Eleazer as “Special Worker in Race Relations”
    Official Report of Five Years Work
    Materials Illustrating Methods and Results
    Notes on the Scottsboro Case, Trial of Heywood Patterson, Decatur, Alabama, April 7-8, 1933
    Complete Notes on Salem Witch Trials by RB Eleazer (notes are not in order)